Guide to the Stanford University, Office of General Studies, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Office of General Studies, records
1954-1962
SC0077
Stanford University. Office of General Studies.
4.5 Linear feet
Records include general administrative files, 1954-57; correspondence dealing with the organization of overseas campus programs in the Far East, 1961-62; and reports, memoranda, minutes, correspondence, and other materials pertaining to the Study of Undergraduate Education, 1954-57. Correspondents include Robert Hoopes, Philip H. Rhinelander, and Donald W. Taylor.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1970.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Description of the Collection
Records include general administrative files, 1954-57; correspondence dealing with the organization of overseas campus programs in the Far East, 1961-62; and reports, memoranda, minutes, correspondence, and other materials pertaining to the Study of Undergraduate Education, 1954-57. Correspondents include Robert Hoopes, Philip H. Rhinelander, and Donald W. Taylor.
Access Terms
Hoopes, Robert.; Rhinelander, Philip H.; Stanford University. Office of General Studies.; Stanford University. Overseas Study Program.; Stanford University. Study of Undergraduate Education.; Taylor, Donald W.; Education, Higher.; Foreign study.
Collection Contents
- Records
  - Minutes of the Committee on Undergraduate Curriculum, 20436 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Memoranda and "Exhibit I", 20479 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Minutes of the Committee on All University Requirements, 20430 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Academic Council Meeting, 3/10/1955-4/23/1955 (Box 1, Folder 1B)
  - Addresses (Box 1, Folder 1C)
  - Correspondence on Advanced Placement Program, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Guide for Twelfth Grade Honors Math Course, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1E)
  - Guide for Twelfth Grade Honors English Course, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1E)
  - Guide for Twelfth Grade Honors Social Studies Course, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1E)
  - Guide for Twelfth Grade Honors Physics Course, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1E)
  - Scoring Manual for the Kent-Rosanoff Word Association Test, Brown University, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Carnegie Corportation, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3A)
  - Occupational Bulletins: Follow-Up Study of Class of 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3B)
  - Scholastic Aptitude Test interpretative documents, 19997 (Box 1, Folder 3C)
  - Conference on College Self-Studies, 12/3/1954-12/4/1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3E)
  - Courses for General Studies Approval, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dartmouth Scans 3-Term Program, 20893 (Box 1, Folder 4A)
  - Departmental Policy on Appointments, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4B)
  - Educational Testing Service, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
  - Educational Testing Service Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
  - Cooperative Test: Psychological Examination, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5C)
  - Cooperative Test: Contemporary Affairs Test, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cooperative Test: English Test, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5E)
  - Cooperative Test: General Achievement Social Studies, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cooperative Test: General Achievement Natural Science, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5G)
  - Cooperative Test: General Achievement Mathematics, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5H)
  - Cooperative Test: General Culture Test, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5I)
  - Faculty Housing, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6A)
  - Forms for Staff (Box 1, Folder 6B)
  - Minutes on Committee on General Studies, 20551 (Box 1, Folder 7A)
  - Staffing of Stanford Center in Germany, 21132 (Box 1, Folder 7B)
  - Green Sheet of Basic Requirements, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7C)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Intellectual Interests Among Students, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Education Association, Association for Higher Education, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16A)
  - National Merit Scholarship Foundation, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16B)
  - History of Painting Syllabus (Box 1, Folder 17A)
  - Procedures Regarding Proposals for Research Grants, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 17B)
  - Psychology 1C Proposal, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 17C)
  - Mr. Philip H. Rhinelander Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Selection of Major Forms (Box 1, Folder 20A)
  - Committee of Educational Inquiry Interim Report on the Semester and Quarter Systems, 20235 (Box 1, Folder 20B)
  - To Dep't Heads, Senior Colloquia, 20740 (Box 1, Folder 20C)
  - Senior Colloquia--Foundation Support, 20842 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Senior Colloquia, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 20E)
  - Statement on Senior Colloquia, 20740 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Memo from Stone, 20950 (Box 1, Folder 20G)
  - Report of Student Group, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 20H)
  - Student-Faculty Committee, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 20I)
  - Taylor, Donald W., 1955 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Undergraduate Incentives, 20792 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Who Should Go To College?, 20148 (Box 1, Folder 24A)
  - Women At Stanford, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24B)
  - Academia Sinica correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Asia Foundation correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Asia Foundation correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Chinese Government Education Dept., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Chinese Government Ministry of Finance, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Educational Institutes correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Educational Institutes, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - General, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - General, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hong Kong (General), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hong Kong Government Education Dept., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hong Kong Committee Report&Notes, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hong Kong, University of: correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - International House, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Mencius Foundation, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - New Asia College correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Physical Facilities correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Chinese Studies Center, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Report on the Possibility of a Stanford Center in Japan (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Stanford Center in Tokyo, 22372 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Memorandum of Actions taken at Meeting of Stanford Tokyo Committee, 22200 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Study Centers Abroad: Tokyo-Collab. Studies, 21788 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence with Rockefeller Foudnation, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Impressions of Japan by Walter Gellhorn, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Study Centers Abroad: Tokyo-Exchange Scholars, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Taipei-Finance, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Taipei-General, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Taipei correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Taipei-Selection & Recruitment, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Taiwan General (Other than Taipei), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - National Taiwan University, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Administrative Memoranda Tokyo Center, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Stanford Center for Japanese Studies General Informaton, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Tokyo General Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Tokyo Selection (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Union Research Institute correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - U.S. Educational Fdn. (Y.T.Shen), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - U.S. Government, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - U.S. Information Service (P.Lowe), 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - U.S. Government correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Joint Recommendation to Academic Council, 20158 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memorandum from President Sterling to members of Academic Council Announcing Meeting, 20478 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memorandum to Academic Council from J.E.Wallace Sterling, 20193 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Fund for Advancement of Education correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Proposal for a Type "B" Grant from the Fund for Advancement of Education, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memorandum from Student Sub-Committee on Advising, Counseling, and Freshman Orientation, 20183 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Analysis of Alumni Questionaire (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Questionnairs--Classes of 1950 and 51; Letter from the President to Accompany, 20363 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Follow-Up Letter for Alumni Questionnaire, 20389 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - IBM Codesheets for Senior and Alumni Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Questionnaire Miscellaneous correspondence, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Aooreciation--Undergraduate Study and the Library, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - David Harris: Aspects of Environment at Stanford, 20043 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Comparative Institutional Scores on CEEB Achievement Tests, 20540 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - A Selection of College and Universities Requiring CEEB Achievement Tests, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - College Board Achievement Test Scores of Stanford Freshmen October 1955, 20428 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memorandum to Members of the University Committee on Counseling, 20387 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Directive to the Subcommittee on the Curriculum, 20375 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subcommittee on Curriculum: Autumn 1955, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Report to Student Committee on Proposed Curriculum Requirements--KIP KOSS, 20438 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letter from President to Deans and Department Heads, 20305 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - President's Letter to Department Heads on Major Requirements, 20376 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Response and Letter of Departmental Major Requirements, 20376 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Replies from Department on Major Requirements in response to President's Letter, 20376 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - English Comp Summary Sheets (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Summary of Results*- Study of Reshman English + Final Report, 20179 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Memorandum to Members of Executive Committee from R. Hoopes and H. Marshall, 20402 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda to Executive and Advisory Committees, Faculty, Student Committee, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee--Correspondence, Memoranda, etc., 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Extra Minutes, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Calendar for Summer Meetings--Exec.--Advisory Com., 1955 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Joint Executive and Advisory Committees--Miscellaneous, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - List of Members of Executive, Advisory Committees and Staff of Study, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Minutes of Joing Executive-Advisory Committee Meeting, 20144 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Joint Executive and Advisory Committee Minutes, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Executive + Advisory Com. Notes on Meetings, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Minutes of Joint Meetings, Executive and Advisory Committees, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Executive and Advisory Committees Minutes--Transcripts, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Experimental Studies Program, Corres., 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Proposal for Committee to Develop an Experimental Studies Program, 20424 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Memorandum to Members of the Faculty, 20066 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - President's Letter to Faculty on Study, 19998 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Faculty--Views on Undergraduate Education and Curriculum, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 2nd Study of Freshman Admissions Variables, 20698 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - D.M. Mendelowitz: Letter on General Education, 20009 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - K.J. Arrow: The General Education Requirements, Social Sciene, 20228 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - H. Skilling: Suggestion for a Basic Plan of General Studies for Undergraduates, 20212 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - The Goals of Stanford University, 20088 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Goheen Report (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Distribution of Grades for Individual Courses, 20191 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - W.W. Harman, Note on the Goals of Humanistic-Social Education, 20225 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Letter from Dr. Felix M. Keesing, 20372 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - A Report on the Stanford Lower Division Language Courses in French, German, and Language Questionnaire, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Language Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Language Questionnaire Germanic-Romanic Statistics, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Mathematics Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Mathematics, Survey of Lower Division Stanford Study of Undergraduate Education, 20304 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - F.W. Strothman: Meditations on the Difference between Training and Education, 20029 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Memoranda, 9/6/1955-4/24/1956 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Memoranda, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Memorandum from Professor Fagan, 20505 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Memorandum to D.W. Taylor from Lois M. Stolz, 20186 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - The New Undergraduate Program at Stanford, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Preliminary Report--Percentage of Units Taken by Freshmen which are Taught by Individuals of Each Rank, 20094 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Percentage of Units Taken by Freshmen which are Taught by Individuals of Each Rank (Med., Educ.), 20106 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Percentage of Units Taken by Undergraduates and Taught by Individuals of Each Rank: Fall Quarter 1954-55, 20157 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Excerpt from Princeton University Brochure, "Special Program in the Humanities", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Outline of Problems for Investigations, 20017 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Student Committee Proposal to Committee on Public Expenses, 20530 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Mr. Hoopes: Requests for Final Sue Report, 21095 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - ROTC--Air Army Navy Marine Sue, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Scope of the Study, 20047 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Copy Questionnaire to Seniors of 1955 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Preliminary Report on Responses to Senior Questionnaire, 20235 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Summary: Questionnaire to Graduating Seniors of 1955, 20403 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Supplementary Totals (Questions 19, 21, 24, 25, 30, 33), Questionnaire to Graduating Seniors, 20486 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Senior Questionnaire Working Papers, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Letter to Stanford Daily by Wilfred H. Stone, 20381 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Departmental Views concerning Teaching and Research, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Demonstration - Faculty Views on Teaching and Research, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Preliminary Summary of Results of Study of Faculty Views on Emphasis Upon Teaching and Research, 1955 Jan 16 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Report of the Subcommittee on Policy Concerning Teaching and Research, 1955 April 5 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Air, Naval, and Military Sciences, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Art and Architecture, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Asiatic and Slavic Studies, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Biological Sciences, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Graduate School of Business, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chemistry and Chemical Engineering, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Classics, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Economics, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - School of Education, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - School of Engineering, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - English, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Geography, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Germanic and Romance Languages, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - History, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Journalism, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Mathematics, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - School of Medicine, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - School of Mineral Sciences, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Music, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Philosophy, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Physics, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Political Science, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Psychology, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Speech and Drama, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Statistics, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous, 1954 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Prelim. Report of Analysis of Size of Undergraduate Classes, 1955 Feb 3 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Memorandum on Undergraduate Colleges R.C. Swank, 1954 Dec 1 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Report of the Subcommittee on the Undergraduate Curriculum as Approved by Exec Com., 1956 Jan 16 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - First Draft of the Report of the Committee on the Undergraduate Curriculum, 1955 Dec 15 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - T.S. Barclay's Statement on Undergraduate Education, 1955 July (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - R.L. Choate: Statement on Undergraduate Education, 1954 Dec 15 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - W.W. Harman, Memorandum on Undergraduate Education, 1954 Dec 1 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Robert Hoopes: Goals of Undergraduate Education, 1954 Oct 31 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Goals of Undergraduate Education - Misc. Drafts, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - George S. Mysers: Statement on Undergraduate Education, 1954 Oct 8 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Lionel Pearson: Statement on Undergraduate Education, 1954 Oct 25 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - H.H. Skilling, the Goals of Stanford Undergraduate Education, 1954 Oct 29 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - E. Swank, Goals of Stanford Undergraduate Education, 1955 Nov 4 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - H.D. Winbigler: Statement on Undergraduate Education, 1955 Feb 7 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - The Goals of Undergraduate Education, 1955 Jan 13 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Study of Undergraduate Education, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Student Committee of the Study of Undergraduate Education, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Undergraduate Education - Unsolicited Letters- Off Campus, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Plan for Undergraduate Library R. Swank, 1955 May 10 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Ten Propositions Concerning the Formulation of teh Four-Year Undergraduate Program, 1955 Sept 28 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Copies - Undergraduate Reports (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - K.F. Reinhardt: What is General Education, 1954 Oct 7 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaneous Working Papers, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Report of Yale College Committee of the General Faculty on Course of Study, 1955 Apr (Box 3, Folder 55)